Finding aid to the Michael and Betsy Kraft collection of Paul Roche papers MRBC.MS.00434
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Michael and Betsy Kraft collection of Paul Roche papers
1963-2004
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Roche, Paul
MRBC.MS.00434
.25 linear feet (1 half legal document box)
Includes typescripts of drafts by poet Paul Roche, handwritten letters and enclosures (photographs, brochures, event pamphlets), and an original drawing by artist Duncan Grant. The materials relate primarily to Paul Roche, a member of the Bloomsbury Group, close friend of Duncan Grant, and member of the Smith College English department in the 1950s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Michael and Betsy Kraft
Biographical / Historical
The Bloomsbury Group was an informal collective of intellectuals, mostly associated with Cambridge University and Kings College London, who banded together in the Bloomsbury district of London as intellectuals and supporters of the arts. Its memebers were artists, art critics, writers, and poets, and included (among others) Virginia and Leonard Woolf, Vanessa and Clive Bell, Duncan Grant, and John Maynard Keynes. The original group was most active between the early 1900s and the 1930s. As they were politically leftist, promoters of personal enjoyment as opposed to Victorian social habits, and post-impressionist artists, they were controversial at the time of their operation.
Duncan Grant and Paul Roche (a member of the later iteration of the Bloomsbury Group) became close friends in the 1970s and took trips together around the world until Grant's death that Paul Roche documented extensively in journals that he later published. Roche was also a member of the Smith College English department in the 1950s, where he met and worked with Sylvia Plath and Ted Hughes.
Michael and Betsy Kraft were friends of Paul Roche's and supporters of his work; this collection contains a sample of their correspondence and works Paul Roche sent to them in his letters.
General
These materials were accepted to bolster our materials related to the Bloomsbury Group, of which Paul Roche and Duncan Grant were members. The published books were accepted to add to our Bloomsbury Group publications and, in the case of 10 of them, as examples of printing and bookbinding by the Writers Workshop in 1990s-2000s India.
Bloomsbury group.; Grant, Duncan, 1885-1978--Correspondence; Roche, Paul (1916-2007); Kraft, Michael B.; Kraft, Betsy; Kraft, Michael B.; Kraft, Betsy
- "Design for Card" by Duncan Grant, approximately 1960; 1 items (1 drawing) (Box 1)
- Correspondence, notes on "Design for Card" by Duncan Grant, 1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Correspondence from Paul Roche to Michael B. Kraft, 1995-2004; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Paul Roche typescripts, 1963; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "With Duncan Grant in Tangier," by Paul Roche, 1993; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "With Duncan Grant in the Highlands," by Paul Roche, 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "Ted, Sylvia, Clarissa, and Paul," by Paul Roche, 1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "Grammar" and "Grammar 2," by Paul Roche, 2000; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "What it Takes to Be Accepted by Britain," by Paul Roche, 2000; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "A Charter of Mutual Respect," by Paul Roche, 2001; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "In the Ambiance of Duncan Grant," by Paul Roche, approximately 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "All My Pretty Ones," and other poetry by Paul Roche, approximately 2001; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "A Key to Prosperity and the Distribution of Wealth," by Paul Roche, 2003; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- "There is Another Way," by Paul Roche, 2004; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Photographs taken by Paul Roche, 2000; 1 folders (1 envelope) (Box 1)